Guide to the German Pamphlet Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
German Pamphlet Collection
1921-1945
MS 735
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(8 boxes, 1 folio)
An artificial collection of German pamphlets, 1921-1945, including material on such topics as: national socialism, armed forces, foreign relations, propaganda, and postwar politics.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by subject.
Scope and Contents
This collection of pamphlets, predominantly out of Nazi Germany, offers a view of that period as seen from the interior. The pamphlets are almost all in German and were intended for home consumption. As a consequence, they convey quite unselfconsciously the programs and goals of the Nazi regime unaffected by attempts to account for outside views. The only pre-Nazi materials in this collection are a group of German propaganda pamphlets and broadsides issued in connection with the plebiscite in Upper Silesia in 1921. (Box 4, Folder 34)
The material is organized by subject, and ranges over military, economic, social, and political topics. Particularly interesting to students of NSDAP history are the pamphlets in the category, "Nazi Party," beginning with a satiric attack on the Weimar Republic, dated 1929, and early election propaganda from 1933 to 1936. Later pamphlets offer a striking insight into how the Party consciously strove to reach every age group and every social level.
A group of pamphlets arranged under the general heading "Armed Forces" and then further divided by the particular arm of the services shows the aims and ideals of the military. We find here accounts of Nazi conquest of territories in Eastern Europe with photographs taken by the invading troops of their own actions. In the pamphlet issued by the Ordnungspolizei, for example, there are photographs of a unit breaking into a synagogue in Riga and loading Jews into trucks. Other photographs show a shattered public building, German soldiers questioning peasants, searching a village, and living in requisitioned houses. Most curious is the light, sporting tone used for the captions: a picture of peasants digging a ditch by the roadside is titled: "Everyone cooperates;"
Among the pamphlets issued by the Wehrmacht are a number of political manuals indicating the responsibilities of officers for the political indoctrination of their troops. The welding of the individual to his unit is demonstrated here in pictures and text with remarkable vividness. Even marriage becomes a political act, and an elaborately illustrated brochure urges the soldier to marry a wife who is racially pure and will bear him and the nation racially acceptable children. Racially impure types are shown for dramatic contrast.
In the section, "Economics," there is a seventy-six page book, in English, Economic conditions in Germany in the middle of the year 1939. Published in June of that year by the Reichs-Kredit-Gesellschaft, it provides an official review of Germany's situation on the very eve of World War II. Two pamphlets by Hjalmer Schacht, also in English, discuss Why Germany and world trade (1935) and Why Germany requires colonies(1936).
The pamphlets in the education section show how educational goals were defined, and also include several examples of textbooks. A sampling of fiction for children is placed under "Juvenile Literature."
Among the few publications intended for distribution abroad is an elaborate photographic essay, with English captions, titled: "What we are fighting for." Another, in French, "Travailler-Vivre" is an attempt to persuade French workers to move to Germany to work. It, too, is extensively illustrated, and is unintentionally revealing. The highly praised living conditions are shown by the photographs to be barracks-like dormitories with rows of double decker iron beds.
Materials dealing directly with the war period, German occupation of conquered territory, and propaganda directed at Allied troops can be found in the World War II Pamphlet Collection, Manuscript Group Number 688.
National socialism; Europe; Germany -- Economic policy -- 1933-1945; Germany -- Politics and government; Germany; Pamphlets
- Inventory
  - Anti-Nazi literature (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Armed forces - Kavallerie (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Armed forces - Kriegsmarine (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Front unter Wasser: Deutscher U-Boot Krieg 1942
    General
    See: box 9
  - Armed forces - Luftwaffe (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Armed forces - medals (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Armed forces - Ordnungspolizei (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Armed forces - Panzertrieppen (Box 1, Folder 6A)
  - Armed forces - S. A. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Armed forces - S. S. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Armed forces - Wehrmacht (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Armed forces - Wehrmacht military manuals (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Armed forces - Wehrmacht political manuals (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Censorship (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Civil defense (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Civilian indemnity (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Conquered territories (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Culture (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Economics (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Education (Box 2, Folder 18)
    No Subnote Content
  - Education - vocational (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Foreign relations (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Foreign relations (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - History (Box 3, Folder 22)
    See also: box 1, folder 8; box 1, folder 9
  - Identification documents (Box 3, Folder 22a)
  - Industry (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Juvenile literature (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Local history - Feldafing (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Memoirs (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Memorabilia (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Military history (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Military manuals (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Military theory (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Nazi Party (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Nazi Party - Sozialismus im Dritten Reich, Nos. 3, 4 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Hitler election propaganda, 1933, 1936, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Plebiscite propaganda - Upper Silesia, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Political tracts (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Propaganda abroad (English language) (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Propaganda abroad (French language) (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Propaganda - patriotic (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Propaganda - patriotic (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Religion (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Territorial questions (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - War guilt (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Weapons (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Youth (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Nazis - Post war
    - Blanke, Gustav H. -Publications and other papers, 1939, 1943, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Armed forces - Wehrmacht (Box 6)
  - Austria (Box 6)
  - Bibliography (Box 6)
  - Croatia (Box 6)
  - Danube region (Box 6)
    [description and travel]
  - Defense (Box 6)
  - Education (Box 6)
    [2 folders]
  - Festivals (Box 6)
  - Fiction (Box 6)
  - Food question (Box 6)
  - Foreign relations (Box 6)
  - Germans in Czechoslovak Republic (Box 6)
  - Goebbels, Joseph, 1897-1945 (Box 7)
  - Hitler, Adolph, 1889-1945 (Box 7)
    [Postcard set: "Aus der Heimat des Führers"]
  - History (Box 7)
  - Italy (Box 7)
  - Japan (Box 7)
  - Ludendorff, Erich Friedrich Wilhelm, 1865-1937 (Box 7)
  - Nationalsozialistiche Deutsche Arbeiter Partei
    - History (Box 7)
    - Jubilee Publications (Box 7)
    - "Kraft durch Freude" (Box 7)
  - Silesia (Box 7)
  - Röhm, Ernst, 1887-1934 (Box 7)
  - Schleswig-Holstein (Box 7)
  - Textbooks
    General note
    - Biology and race (Box 7)
    - Composition (Box 7)
    - Folk history (Box 7)
    - Folk poetry (Box 8)
    - Geography (Box 8)
    - History (Box 8)
    - Language (Box 8)
  - Versailles, Treaty of, 1919 June 28 (Box 8)
  - World Power Conference, 2nd, Berlin, 1930 (Box 8)
  - War literature (Box 8)
  - l. Die Kampfschar. Für die Mitkämpfer, herausgegeben/ von Fr. von der Ropp November 1933. 5 p. (mimeographed) (Box 9, Folder folio)
  - 2. BERLINER ILLUSTRIERTE ZEITUNG (Box 9, Folder folio)
    Sonderheft. Der 21. März 1933. Die Staatsfeierlichkeiten bei der Reichstagseröffnung.
    Sonder=ausgabe der Berliner Illustrirten. Die Trauer=feierlichkeiten am 6. und 7. August 1934. 9 August 1934.
    Nummber 32. 12 August 1934. (Memorial issue for Hindenburg).
  - 3. Deutschland dankt ihm... München, Hugo Fischer, [1935?]. 24 p. Rotogravure publication depicting the accomplishments of the Hitler regime. (Box 9, Folder folio)
  - 4. REX, 5e annee, no.10. 6 Mars 1936. Leon Degrelle, editor. Belgian publication sympathetic to the Hitler regime. (Box 9, Folder folio)
  - 5. Wiedemeyer, Gerhard. Front unter Wasser: Deutscher U-Boot (Box 9, Folder folio)
    Krieg 1942. Berlin, Oberkommando der Kriegsmarine, 1942?
    46 p. illus. Mit Beitragen von Dr. Adolf Halfeld/ Dr. P. Reibisch, u.a.
  - 6. DER JUNGE NATIONALSOZIALIST. Blatt der N.S. Jugendbewegung. München. 1 Jahrgang, nr. 5. Mai 1952. With stamp on cover: Probenummer. Laid in a leaflet addressed to "Münchener Parteigenossen." (Box 9, Folder folio)
  - 7. Der Allemanne. Kampfblatt der Nationalsozialisten Oberbadens./ Freiburg i. Br. 31 März 1933. (Box 9, Folder folio)
  - 8. VOLKISCHER BEOBACHTER. Süddeutsche Ausgabe. München. (Box 9, Folder folio)
    31 Januar 1933
    6 März 1933
  - 9. DEUTSCHE ALLGEMEINE ZEITUNG. Berlin. (electrostatic copies) (Box 9, Folder folio)
    83 Jahrgang Nr.53, 23 Februar 1944
    83 Jahrgang Nr.269, 1 Oktober 1944
    83 Jahrgang Nr.270, 3 Oktober 1944
  - 10. Status Quo. 150 000 marschieren. Status Quo. Bilder vom (Box 9, Folder folio)
    6. Januar in Saarbrücken. Saarbrücken, Volksstimme, [1935].
    [4] p. illus.